hello thanks for joining us on this
video welcome I will give some context
for my conversation with Johannes our
eminent true thinker on Heidegger and
learning how to die essentially learning
how to die well I would say but first
let me sit give some housekeeping so a
few things circling my company the
circling Institute as is currently doing
all of their work online so we have
circling we have a circling weekend
coming up that'll be on zoom' july 11th
and 12th we have the art of circling a
year-long training the online version is
open for registration now and there's a
Thursday evening every Thursday evening
we have an open to everybody drop in
circle so links for all that below
I think there's discounts on the weekend
and on a registration for the artists
circling all that stuff will be in the
emails yeah this one you register so
hope to see you there also if you're
interested in working with me in
coaching one-on-one go ahead and iam
email me that is below and we'll get in
contact or I'll cover
Costin what it's all about
alright so so Johannes so I think some
first some of you for most of you I
would imagine you probably watched my
other discussions with Johannes I'm
always really struck with him about the
in fact we talked about in this video
the the sense of the divine madness of
two wakened in you like the
philosophical awakening right is
precisely awakening to something that
you can't ever quite reach right in fact
it awakens in some sense we talked a
little bit about this about
perhaps what Heidegger's disclosing when
he says death right not death like an
event in the future not not your demise
but the the deepest horizon the deepest
horizon that is also most near that that
that in a certain sense allows it's like
it allows thinking itself to disclose
right so we talked a lot about right
about death about thought a radical
understanding that Heidegger really
revealed about the movement of thinking
and its relationship to negativity or
the nothing or concealment
and I and it's so interesting because I
just really appreciate Heidegger and and
in philosophy and all the conversations
with the johannes and essentially all
the conversations I've been having seems
to me that what what all of that has in
common right all these conversation all
the people philosophy to me the thing it
reveals what I'm most interested in
which is like that which can't be fully
fully revealed or taken over but the
mystery the sense of getting closer and
closer to the mystery of what it is to
be and know awaken that and allow that
to reveal your life and how you respond
right and everything that we do so in
that way of revealing like allowing that
which is concealed to to come into
unconcealed meant without
without making it a position but opening
what's beyond the horizon right what's
most near to us so we just get into that
sense of it that hermie Annette
extensive of speaking into that so it
really it was a really rich conversation
and just an opportunity to really see
somebody who I would say true think are
a true philosopher who you could just
feel it in him you know he can't not do
it
right so and also he's got a he's got a
whole thing opening up for him in terms
of teaching essentially the university
level classes open to everybody and
seminars happening online and and and we
talk a lot about that so uh little the
links for his upcoming classes below
please check that out I'm gonna be I'm
gonna be diving into this one on death
and being until we talk about about that
a lot as well so enjoy
I'm recording all right right now no
good action so welcome welcome
again welcome again you have been you
have been like I think you're a couple
of things you're discovering something
through teaching on online and doing
doing these classes online that's one
it wasn't I think you've just kind of
emerged in the process of being in
quarantine and starting a channel but
what I I'm actually I'm pretty
interested in like what this reveals
about like our time right like
but you're actually teaching high
daguerreian intense high daguerreian
courses right outside of the university
system and people are coming and they're
liking it and they're paying for it and
just and as you said just - you're
actually just there to learn for its own
sake yeah that's really cool yeah we
started um to begin at the beginning
right that's always the poor kid you
know weirdly enough I had the idea to
put up videos positive videos at least
six or seven years ago when I moved to
London twenty thirteen or fourteen never
did it of course and it was there was a
moment and I finished my PhD in 2018 and
then moved back to London in the fall to
take up a very small position at
Birkbeck and who is another day laborer
you know right as we as we laborers of
the spitters are once or I have to do
actually it cuz we also have to eat
really enough and then and then I
finally said I had a couple of weeks off
and I sat down on my now infamous sofa
upstairs the velvet sofa which was
previously owned by Oscar Wilde just
kidding
and and said down and recorded a lecture
which which is on the origin of thinking
which is basically just an
interpretation of an attempt in the
philosophical interpretation of Stanley
Kubrick's 2001 a Space Odyssey now put
it up on in on Instagram on YouTube and
I think I got about two or three views
four of them mine and it took it's
really weird because but but then it's
it's it started is how
thing because I had the idea anyways to
do it um I think it would be easy to say
it's out of necessity because you you're
not really allowed what it is that you
want to teach at University but I think
it would be short-sighted to call it an
SST it's rather that because then you
know then you're gonna be a romantic and
we want to be classical which means
there's a full flowing
yes saying and it simply just it it
begins to flow and it needs to be it
needs to be out there I mean not
everything needs to be shared not
everything needs to be recorded there's
always the as always the notebook of the
think of which there are two or three
chests here on this desk yeah yeah which
may or may not find the way since of
publication here's my my bigger one
where I'm working on a full book that's
the ones that we're gonna find after you
after you die and and and terrible
things in there uh this is actually I'm
working on a on a on the first book in
in German which will be an original work
of philosophy um so not no longer a
commentary but you know even commentary
is what is common carrier the commentary
has become to you know comment on what
someone else has said about what someone
else is said about what someone else has
said commentary means to think with
meant re means to think can come or
cornice is with so comment re is to
think with someone um and this is what
thinking always has to do and what so
what I did with with the channel was
never to was never to get you know you
could make a video that is very you know
really well produced and talk about
something that everybody else is talking
about right now right som something
political and then you you know this
movement through this lens right or the
critical theory of Jordan Peterson that
that's always a hit or the mythology of
you okay that gets you gets you know I
just sat down one of the weirdest videos
I did was just with my with my being
copy of silence I being in time reading
the
Paige in a way that it would just come
and one of the one of the one of the
first videos I recorded was on
Heraclitus amenities and that's the one
you found right right
yeah um yeah so those are I think I at
least like to think that they are quite
rigorous
yeah but then again not rigorous in a
sense in which you would have to be now
in order to get published yes yes the
thing that you you see the you see the
the Machine of academia and what demands
of a few in order to get a population or
to get a job which is basically you are
you you you die by numbers so it's a
it's a death by numbers to speak in the
slogan um which means you know you have
to publish in high-impact journals as
they call it and then when you do that
you you get you get high impact yeah so
you're constantly evaluated yeah so how
do you flip this I mean something I
learned very early on what you flip it
by playing you're still playing the
numbers game right
right because you're right to get you
need to get to some subscriber level
yeah nodes I get some traction to have
some what call that they call following
yeah in order to get some people who are
actually really you know willing to to
sign up for your courses which is not
actually the third one now I'm running
in a third course this year right right
and there will be a fourth one yeah late
late in the summer or Nietzsche this one
now some death and Heidegger on death
yeah the one before was not actually on
Heidegger the one before was on idleness
which was on Plato Aristotle Cicero
Russell Nietzsche homeboy Heidegger one
lecture yes and chose his PIPA there was
own to work etc right and and also again
possibly the escapable
I'm see in with with these with the
video I mean as you know I find it also
quite dangerous but nothing is just
promising a utopia there's the danger of
turning something into into
entertainment and background noise oh
yeah but then again you can cut through
so much with it and you can cut through
the gate
keepers yeah I you can you can not even
cut through because that sounds all too
aggressive I would rephrase it as I you
know you can just let them be yeah yeah
let them be gatekeepers over here yeah
and and build your own space somewhere
else or a we're through through through
some eccentricity people actually begin
to listen yeah that is a quite a monkey
or to do yeah I think that's a key word
what if people listen yes yes yes I mean
you know if this is if there's no status
in this right this is the funny thing
also that there's nothing actually
probably the opposite um at least but
it's changing a bit now I guess it that
might there might be the usual status
hierarchies to but I think it's for me
it was in the beginning just a way of
experimenting with with text I had
written to see whether they actually
make sense right but also the ability to
build something in such a way that if
there is you know I really wanted to
teach a course I'm hiding on Tekonsha I
asked the University where I met idea
whether I could teach it and it's
practically impossible yeah yeah even
though even though students actually
demand it
there's no I mean in pure market terms
there's no higher demand and for Adorno
and hiding at the moment mmm-hmm right
because you know meaning is as you know
is speaking as long as but meaning isn't
collapsing yeah those are figures who
have attempted to provide answers right
to what's going on and others of course
to but it's it's it's it's made and even
those who are in positions at
universities where they can teach what
they would like to teach it takes years
right sometimes until you can actually
do it and here's there's no the stomach
if you've got something to say to share
for example I've written
book on how to go on death and peeing
which is about to be published by
Springer yeah and congratulations on
that by the way thank you sir yeah and
the the course is on based on this book
and on seven years of research mm-hmm no
right my question maybe I'm just overly
pragmatic but might the possibility of
me would be either to wait forever until
I'm allowed perhaps that I could teach
this or I just do it myself we've
actually already filled the Saturday
seminar and there was so much interested
I'm offering now Sunday's as well yeah
we're putting a little be putting a link
to the what you're talking about because
it's so in other words you're doing a
course right now on on death Heidegger
and death yeah it starts so the seminars
start in two weeks from now yeah so I'll
put links below so people will want to
join join that I'll be in it yes you use
useful the last one on hide again
delicious yeah yeah and technology yeah
yeah they're awesome they're really
awesome
I really would be Zen masterpiece
yes it really was my lectures yeah I'm
humbled but of course I agree but how
couldn't I agree but this this was a
tremendous experience because there's
lots of people signed up actually an
artist from New York Kevin McCoy is his
name he signed up for it and he I think
he had a bit of tremon that's at high
school and he was younger and I went
through the all the modes of stealing of
gifted right of positionality yeah and
he he apparently and we saw this in the
procession or yeah he built he builds a
new or envisioned a new art project
because of this lecture on Stalin on
positioning and position added yeah yeah
um these are the weird things that
happen with it right yeah it's yeah I'm
just imagining just that well a couple
of things I'm noticing just that you're
able to do this right you're able to
just say what you think and where your
thinking is going
and then have people and offer that and
then have people want to participate um
not for a degree now for an outcome not
for but because they want to learn yes
there's something about that that's so
encouraging right and so strange that it
that you're becoming a new point in
which we get to find that out right
where people there are people that want
to learn for learnings sake yeah that
there's big about that that's is so
encouraging to see happen yeah I mean
did there's plenty of reasons for it and
we don't meet to get into it why I think
would philosophy though specifically it
you know it's almost almost it's almost
bound to happen with philosophy first um
but philosophy leaves and you know
everything's quite open there's no
evaluation I'm no one one of the
greatest things he would should I say
are even the Janaka once said in an
electric horse that he gave 10 years ago
boards on oh I said how should I
evaluate you on whether you have
understood the eternal recurrence of the
like in nature yeah you have understood
this 80% 90% yeah yeah
either it's understood and thought
through or it's not yeah how do you its
and other than that is it there's a
tendency universities in anyway you know
everyone tries to be a B+ or and and
then operates within that framework that
that's true for young scholars as well
as as young students there's no one who
just diverts that they've enjoyed
experiments with something yeah I'm
extremely adapted to the machine to the
wheel work and also lying I think you
know young scholars I think have
eternity to lie either they're quite
happy where they are or did they just
you know I'm just gonna be we're just
gonna compromise for the next 10 years
until I have tenure which no longer
exists for most place and then when I
have some position in some power then I
can finally say what I'd like to say
once you know once you're at this point
you've already lost it but in terms of
learning you know speaking of the one
I'm trying to build an online Academy
right you know that halcón right the
hell can kill you oh yeah Robin yeah um
and you know there's a forum and
everything else the students can sign up
for the forum and be in touch with
others it's becoming a bit of almost
like a think tank right um is weird but
you know people who exchange ideas on
there and and gather knowledge but
Helmke on I mean we can talk about what
helicam means but there's a wonderful
quote from shelling the German
philosopher we said the following all
rules for study are summed up in this
one learn only in order to create right
that's learn the light order to only
create right learn only in order to
create yes which is from his book on
university studies and what the
university should be as a place yeah and
this is the light mu T of the halcyon
Academy and then I you know I've written
the text on this and I say we're very
not at all about meaningless credentials
or pieces of paper instead our focus is
on the true formation education of human
beings maybe flourish and fully become
who we are our seminars are spaces of
ultram Dignitas idleness with dignity
free from instrumental rationality and
the demands of the market right because
when you deal with students when you're
dealing with very often as people who
are young
yeah scared and anxious about the chalk
market yeah and also people go into
death yeah and I think philosophy is is
you know the first discipline - one of
the first disciplines to do this because
of the nature of philosophy well it's
it's always you know philosophy is in
the tension between life and thinking
and it has to articulate
life without for
into life just like Socrates always has
one foot on the market square but does
not become really a market participant
and here's I mean as all you know issues
we could go into but I I think also that
it's when someone gets bitten by
philosophy very young
someone person let's say you're 15 you
read Nietzsche
maybe Camus you can come or pray or you
know was usually one of the excess
tension is so someone like Heidegger
perhaps oh she's not a shorter text and
then live you know as they say speaking
gnomes and Sophocles life happens yeah
you have to start making money you have
to leave your home perhaps and you got
them to the world but it if it once has
gotten under your skin they will never
leave you and when I see with many of
the students is that there's something
that they they want to understand and
it's incredible and you have someone you
have a guy who runs a tree to school in
Texas a lawyer a lawyer in Florida right
really you know high very intense job
yeah I like yeah he said he's actually
he's a client of mine too oh yeah yeah
yeah he's a great great yeah then you
have yeah there's another guy who's
doing a postdoc and engineering at a
very prestigious Ivy League university
there's a very nice gentle man up in
Toronto was from Turkey originally I
think you know I think they all for some
reason or other want to understand wish
to understand something yeah yeah always
have long to read philosophy very often
thought what happens is we go to
university yeah you then oh this is
philosophy Wow it's sterile and dead
yeah right yeah it's it's it's it
doesn't happen it doesn't occur when I
left boys are no I had ancient Greek at
school regret the original texts and
like so
this is how you become accustomed to
this way by thinking right I came to the
old town idea de janeiro as my teacher
there and I thought well this is all the
philosophy well I'm just going to study
philosophy now right
and I came to other places and then it
took up until it took me you know there
were a couple were some we're really
good brothers it was just a job it was a
nine to five and then goodbye
um and then I was very lucky again with
my supervisor McKay a little bit a key
he's also just a very good think a very
good pedagogue that's that that's so
rare is this someone who lets you roam
alright and lets you walk off whoa and
then and only then rears you back in
right brings you back when you get to
lost when you get when you go too far
astray yeah yeah well it's it's you you
have to be able to get math a bit when
you write the peach tease I was lucky
with my supervisor but I don't it's
becoming all the more and closed and and
sterile so what this provides really
enough is this digital space I mean is
this the possibility to bring people in
who really just want to read and write
yeah sometimes even write it is one of
the things that that came out of these
we never planned for a pro seminar a
public Pro seminar yeah in the how to
get the Lewis course yeah and then we
just came up with it at somebody's
actually they're quite good maybe they
want to present something offer it to
them and then someone actually signed up
so I offered the same thing again with
the idleness with dignity courses so
that this will happen next week yeah um
and then during this time I said you
know this was a seven week seven
consecutive Saturdays is does almost
that's almost an entire term yeah UK
yeah which is ten weeks um what some of
them just started writing yeah and so I
say young share the
you know put it up on put it on the
forum write and comment on each other
and then we can you can present both of
these essays you know and then you get
these emails from some kid who's up in
Canada was that you know thank you for
giving me the gift of thinking well the
someone else was you know it's very
inspired now again to learn it's a
doctor in South Africa
yeah um because you can't learn just on
your own right all right also the the
teacher is the learner and yeah yeah um
and the teacher needs to be very aware
of this also that you actually you know
right well the one who's learning yeah
look I had a great sense of letting
learn yeah yeah
and the and and I yeah so the the
approach is just a different one because
there's this you know there's no there's
no honor I mean there's no status that
comes with having having been in an
online course with me there's nothing
that comes from that except for perhaps
something learned someone's the engineer
um was not going to Cornell said in an
email
he's now more focused hmm after that he
said oh I noticed that has noticed this
over the seven weeks yeah yeah and I'm
not trying to make it instrumental or
operational you know you can do of
course you will be more focused no but
this was one of the ways in which it
translated into into the practical in
the sense that when you share
conversation or with others or in a very
focused manner and the wit thing is also
no one ever looks at their phone during
my online seminars but they knew all the
time during my you're a my because it's
weird this kind of the focus is you know
it's much more radical here if I yeah
then in the classroom they was looking
at their phone yeah it's not a fit not
none of the questions they would have to
worry about is it relevant for the exam
right here's what I always ask my
students first seminar make sure I
always ask why are you here hmm remember
I did this five years ago for the first
time
and warwick and a first-year students
first semester ancient Greek philosophy
well asked why are you here and one of
them raised their hands and this is
relevant for the exam right right and
I'm and I said no you you know you you
have to wonder why are you here
the good thing is the place I'm at now
is a bit different someone actually said
I'm looking for meaning but I think with
these voluntary online courses that are
very high level they're difficult
they're properly academically
philosophical but they they do address
the kind of people who really want and
there's many out there yeah we didn't
get the chance to do a PhD yeah or we
didn't get the chance to stay in
learning because as it is we said before
life happens they have to make ends meet
um and then you get isolated right
because everyday conversations are about
Netflix shows and whatever else nonsense
um and very often people are isolated
yeah and and one too I mean literally
what these seminars are about they're
about a community yeah about people it's
like going to school you know the
university you become friends with the
people you're around with right the
seminars are also a you know they're
philosophical and there's right now the
rigorous yeah I'm big there's a bit of
banter obviously and and forget to stay
in touch right it's up to the students
but usually actually one of the things
that happened with the I to get the
Lewes course with Justin Murphy a
reading group formed the reading Aaron's
doing her and Nietzsche and the doorman
they're still meeting apparently hmm hmm
that's um that's that's awesome well I
think one of the things he said was you
know eight he said you
they wanna they want to learn something
like there is a sense when you when you
said that the the the what to learn what
I even I could imagine even if they
could say what they want to learn it
probably didn't actually it wouldn't
it's not representational there's
something beyond there's a mystery
there's a there's a something beyond the
horizon that calls forth the learning in
the sense that you're talking about
that seems to be what that seems to be
to point to what being like education
actually is right like what is it that
wants to learn what evokes learning
right and it's so interesting to see
that like one of the things I I would
imagine how successful this is unfolding
cuz basically you're talking about like
oh yeah we I did this course I put up a
few videos it went really really well
it did another one and then people that
then the students of their own doing
started to write papers and then it's
like well now they're gonna start
presenting them and now people that are
teaching that you're there's a whole
thing unfolding
what's cool about it to me is it it's it
seems to be grounded in that spark of
they come wanting to bit wanting to
learn something right yeah so the whole
thing is like the whole thing is like
grounded in that expresses that and is
emerging and you're responding to it um
yeah really I'm just I'm just responding
to that to which I've always responded
yes which which is I've had two great
teachers in my life and I'm counting I'm
not counting the PhD because maybe maybe
because then it would be maybe a bit
more but this the the most formative
years were when I was much younger so
yeah there's every good cheese max
culturally one of my really good friends
he's an extremely good teacher
Steven Holgate at Warwick who teaches
eagle
very good teacher too as that before me
getting to be staking my supervisors is
just a really wonderful teacher but the
most formative years are for her for me
my time at ganache is high school and
Germany and and of course and that the
university is in Italy 30 which now is
in Italy and I'm in in in Augsburg in my
hometown it was Mattias father who was
my teacher of
Greek and he was able to bring to life
the Greek language so that it wasn't
just you know ornaments that he would
use for himself
no it did everything began to the
meeting began to show this sounds Pitino
which she wanted but it's just it was
meaningful that these texts became
meaningful they showed their profundity
uh I read Plato and Aristotle to Kitty's
Erik lightest etc paninis in MB original
and thanks to what guy was a terrible
student
thanks to or pupil that's probably
thanks to this one teacher Matias father
who was able to teach Greek in such a
way that the language was not sterile
and dead and some bushwa exercise of
intellectualism no but it it it was
living and breathing and it ignited the
pool I ate so on the ever-living fire of
which Heraclitus speaks huh yeah and
then you did its once this gets you this
is what always did this what drove me
into academia cuz I thought this would
be the one place it still has it and
unfortunately it's it's it's not I'm not
saying you know I'm not one of those who
say old is all gonna come to an end no I
don't think so but I think it's probably
no longer the right place for those who
just who are young and do it out of a
genuine passion right you you let me you
lock me into this room here there's two
things is gonna happen I'll sit down and
read I'll sit down and write and I'll
make music right right yes it's all
right it's all the same that's awakened
in you it's all there's nothing I didn't
yes yeah yeah
it's a constant if it's so in other
words it's a cut it's a constant madness
Minea yeah Munya glioma nia film anya
it's a constant divine matheus yeah that
pulls the soul of the philosophers Plato
says in the Phaedrus the Nima the
remembrance towards the most divine
things which you know it's as good to
censor and everything that's that's
intelligent has already been thought
that the Wonder is you have to think it
again and again and again yeah and it
just so happens that when I'm left to my
own devices like so I'm not really
sitting still and meditating yeah my
meditation is in writing and in reading
yeah we're meditating means in this old
sense of Perry on the millet attempt and
yeah it means what to take into
consideration and profound care
everything that is insofar that it is
this is what meditation doesn't is what
the thinker does yeah right now I think
perhaps to some degree this X you know
I've been described as eccentric by my
students at university so I didn't you
know that's probably accurate um
eccentricity doesn't bode very well at
this point in in institutions but it
builds quite well right online yeah and
yes and you said something about
learning and studying and education it's
I mean I don't even like the word
education because it's you're pulling
something out if someone leading
something out yeah um the the pedagogue
by dog again yes it has to do with
leading the child that's true there's
some leadership but the determined word
build on the Contin
buildings for me that better and I think
you know there wasn't there was a time
in the university would have could have
been like this you know even with and
when Heidegger was still a professor
that was was he was able to teach
whatever he wanted we talked about this
before and you you read someone like
I've got fifty you know or someone like
Paul Network who was hiding his mentor
at mob work
do you read these texts and this this
was a lecture course really assigned me
huh
right so and yeah but the the learning
is it comes from it so here's a nice
word yeah
feedback not a nice word actually
students in now dinosaur institutions
want feedback right feedback is a word
from cybernetics as intro tech had
pointed out to me here our common friend
right and you know in Oh feedback
students want feedback they don't
there's no feedback in that sense in the
seminars yeah there is an open
discussion in a dialogue which does not
mean by the way a conversation between
two people but a thinking and reasoning
through da da means through yeah
a thinking and reasoning through and
they then in true sense commenting
comment are means to think with um and
from from from you know the weird thing
is that what I found is that not many
people take philosophy seriously in
philosophy departments I take it very
seriously I think that without
philosophy we do not know how to
articulate what it means to be and what
it means to be human
yeah yeah that profound it's not just
some exercise that's interesting or
relevant no it's fun fundamentally
necessary yeah yeah and I think
taking it that seriously speaks to those
who also know that there's something
that it's really profoundly important
yeah yeah who we are and that itself is
the death you use the word spark that
sparks something that sparks the genuine
interest which means to be with and
within yep and as we've got him out here
mr. 50:50 says at some point a letter to
Reinhold the Geist is fucking spoon the
sparks of the Spirit are flying ah
sparks to fly as the Rolling Stone said
yes yes yes so this box of the spirit of
flying and this is something that either
it happens or it doesn't happen and it
happens when when I think it happens
when the teacher takes the takes the
subject seriously and then it attracts
the kinds of students who don't have do
they don't have they don't have to be
there yeah lay it out yeah yeah nothing
for no reason other than huh right that
that draws me in for whatever reason
yeah I need to hear right I want to
understand it what's it what's
interesting what's interesting about
that that sense of that like that which
I'm drawn to understand yeah that seems
to be like a completely different
phenomena because it's it seems like
that that which is drawn to understand
essentially what you're especially in
what you're teaching right is it's not
like they're gonna it's not a conclusion
it doesn't seem to be about curiosity it
seems to be grounded in wonder right
like curiosity is that sense of like if
you like if you increase curiosity gets
more and more unpleasant we're wonder if
you increase it right it becomes more
desirable to have it so there's that
sense of the inexhaustible that like
actually to want and this is this is
what were we start to get into to the
sense of death which I think
he's also speaks to reverence and how to
revere Aref genuine reverence play
interview because reverence has so much
to do with an awareness of your own kind
of FINA to door your limitation but
you're open to and aware that something
is beyond right inexhaustible at the
same time and it's so it reverence is
that sense of like I am drawn to and to
be with in honor of it's beyond us right
that so it's a way of it's a way of like
not of allowing something beyond the
horizon or miss that the mystery to
unfold without raping it of its of its
unknown miss or its mystery right that
sense of reverence into I know that for
me like because I didn't go go into this
I kind of did this at I just started
reading Heidegger I don't even know why
but but stumbling through it right with
my dyslexia and everything like that but
I think what it what what tighter er did
for me anyways in reading philosophy did
for me was that I was so clear that I
was now understanding what when I was
reading but something was disclosed yeah
and and the the whoof like there was
something about the walk that the text
took me on break it was like the walk
that it took me on understanding like in
the process of understanding and not
understanding that I got closer to this
thing that was ever disclosed and just
heightened
Heidegger never like revealed it in some
sense that I can possess but that's just
awakened I mean that just awakened
everything for me
yes and
I think you know terms of processing
that's we want to possess we want to you
know sometimes I said there's nothing
more more meaningless than my my doctor
teacher my doctorate title I rarely use
it I really think of it well because it
is it's just it is actually quite
meaningless the title itself is you know
an appreciation of some work I've done
what math as more as the is the years
spent on this question and what has
opened up through it and you said you
know you read high to get he have no
idea what's going on I'm telling you the
story now going to tell you story now of
how this project started to that I knew
left was done in 2012 went to the UK I
knew I would like I would like to do a
PhD here I wasn't sure if maybe
Nietzsche maybe Heidegger maybe
something as entirely
I thought I'm an autodidact on Heidegger
so I had no formal pause on Heidegger
until the second term of my PhD when I
took a course with Miguel to boost eggie
an introductory course to being in time
for his second year students and he said
to me oh you know you'll have had so
many courses you there's nothing new I
can see you know I didn't tell him but I
didn't have any cause I'm hiding it
before so I read being in time on my own
on top of my MA studies and Kinko's
nuttin which which was a really a good
time because I I read Condor an Indian
philosophy with a very good teachers
name was will resolution or I was very
open-minded Nietzsche with Ken teams and
Andrew Huddleston which is also very
good um so I read very broadly in terms
of
continental and non continental
philosophy but no Heidegger's Ironhide
he got my own and noticed and I couldn't
articulate it but I noticed that death
is very prominent in being in time and
then really you think about us designed
some tortilla being towards death it
sounded like it's being itself that's
towards death and again let's come back
the question of the book is not how do I
live my life right um
it's all about the everyday you know
it's a bit about the everyday but it's
actually the first paragraph is become
the necessity of the explicit work of an
explicit repetition of the question of
ping oh the necessity and as you know in
the first paragraph it says they come to
mafia petit des rouges the gigantic
battle for being and I thought there
must be something to do and of course
time as well death has to do with time
for reasons that we can get into at some
other point I is quite has to do with
concealment - right and the sheltering
an arid heilige Iran what is metaphysics
in 2013 this short lecture he gave in
1929 when he came to Phi book it was his
first lectures welcoming lecture Aretas
in their staff - you take mention to
state library of munich anything
note that he added in 1949 which is the
adhan Alta to the published text it says
they're told the stability designs the
means death the mountain range of being
right what is this supposed to me yeah
so 2013 it became clear I'd like to work
for nothing I emailed me ill and he said
this sounds quite interesting you know
right of proposal he accepted the other
races history but it took me so I this
is seven years of research now at this
point I just finished the book on death
and being and Heidegger because I think
that when you look for an answer to the
question of being you have to look to
death yeah it is in death death comes
back everywhere death is everywhere all
the time
gay Billick Heidegger wants to
understand not just as mountain range
but also as the concentration of all the
sheltering harbouring concealment and in
this sense you stallion which is the
concentration of a forceful positing and
making available and controllable right
in this sense gift L is the opponent of
death it must work against death because
it allows for no sheltered Ness for no
harbored Ness for no concealed Ness
which means being held yeah being held
and home yeah that's what gift still
hates and if general wants to eradicate
this and you see the transhumanists and
post humanists fighting battling against
death without death saying you know this
is too much of the slow but without
death there is no human being human
being not ISA I'm so nice a human being
one has to listen human being does not
mean some you know some someone over
here and someone over the human being
that could still be a mass of humanoids
right but no human being in the sense of
an openness to the question of being and
thinking itself and language would then
be eradicated the war against
which the war against meaning is on the
same is the same attack as the war
against death yeah yeah
when Heidegger works this out from very
different angles and you know this is
why the the world that is not an
opposition but that is also possible in
epoch of gifts tell which he calls the
fourfold in English they feared the
regions of the for the gathering of the
four with mortals and divinities and
earth and sky yeah mortals and he says
they're mortals of those who were
capable does the official translation
all sailing orders of death as death now
the German word here instead of capable
is Thea Mugen that Mugen means that you
like to some degrees are not capable at
all but actually to be open by by a by
virtue of liking yeah being open to
something as something and death as
death is a strange formulation yeah it's
it's it's an existential truisms to say
most of those who are that's completely
ridiculous that's redundant yeah how a
logical speech Heidegger says something
else we are not mortal just by the mere
biological fact that our cells you know
stop to split and whatever they do then
we die right no no we have to be able to
learn how to die and we are so we aren't
quite deprived of this way of little of
existing we don't want to think of it in
this way the philosophy has always meant
to learn how to die right Cicero says
Socrates says it Michel de Montaigne you
don't even have to quote anyone it's
about learning to die and it's because
even even thinking for thinking it's a
thinking does not begin with something
yeah thinking itself
positivism yes positivism says here's
the book and here's the pen yeah
well mister positivism how do you
differentiate the two and already you
already you're in negation and that's
already not possible you know positivist
has collapsed near collapse decades ago
for this very reason but um the thinking
itself
withholds itself friend it's it's not
available it actually is the exact
opposite it's it's it's with the drawing
and the thought becomes to think
withdrawal specifically right right and
this is what death is a window for us
into it this is why death is the the
highest testimony Heidegger says of
being with the why and very early on
this is the this is the to this the
first so the first lecture and seminar
is on being in time those are the first
part of the book which will be out kind
of I think in October it is on on design
in being in time and I felt zoom mobi
bundles summary Bundys right I think he
also in English and this is the response
high degrees in 1925 when he was in my
blog to Descartes and today cards dictum
of the cogito ergo sum I think therefore
I am
and Heidegger says this mented formula
would make any sense at all but to make
any sense at all then it would be some
more people knows which means I am and I
am in meaning in so far I am directed
towards my death not as mortally ill he
says yeah but it is this and you know we
have to distinguish between the later in
the earlier hiding here but you know how
they go it's about directedness to us is
utmost limit in which we always already
are so you see the representational
account things of limit as something
that that limits the the border between
two countries yeah but no the the limit
is justice speaks in to the limit
situation is imminently where we are
hey death is imminently the moment where
we are this is what Heidegger says in as
soon as we are we're old enough to die
he goes ask the same thing
Hegel says the very same thing right
right
it's we are in Heineken booze
radicalizes even further
yes striding through the mountain range
of being in our life we dwell in death
right right
and hence also the inherent danger it's
not just homely I think there's there's
something pretty 3/12 we dwell and Beth
right so the thing of you know and this
is I have to say that this one
what Heidegger's um revealing and when
he talks about death for Americans this
one is almost impossible
great like the moment you represent it
as either as is your demise or an event
or things you know it's the world what
was it the world collapse yeah is he
were talking about the birth the
Berkeley Heights Berkeley High
daguerreian professors it's almost in
actually in listening to that video that
were you were going over that like the
misconceptions of life you the Dreyfus
kind of people and the misconceptions of
death where they it was it's almost like
they get that they don't understand it
in fact you can listen to Dreyfus right
you can listen to him in his course it
is it's actually I really like listening
to him because he's he's getting up
there and he's he's genuinely stumped
and trying to work it out but there is
this quality of there is this quality of
this sense of like they get it they
don't understand something and so they
they search for the thing that um you
could say like that basically represents
they get it right and once if they can
get it right then they could stop
thinking and then they can go on with
the rest of the thing it's kind of like
a knit companion yeah there's a quality
of like figuring out is this yeah I
think it's more grounded in curiosity
than it is wonder essentially right
that where it's irritating it's a
struggle but there is a sense of like
there is a sense of like if we can get
it right we can stop the struggle
whereas with Heidegger I always get the
sense that no like that you know that
you're on the right track when when
something lose everything you lose more
and more you lose everything you let go
the thinking of the agnus
I mean it means is to let go of
everything familiar yeah you really are
and that's what representation seems to
do is that when I go because I know this
happens a lot when I'll talk about
Heidegger right like with people they'll
go oh that's like that's what the dow is
say or that's what the did it is a or
something like that and I'm like wait a
minute
even if that's correct it's not going to
be true right because because you're
just gonna bring your basically you just
stop thinking if you say it's like this
because you just brought it into to the
realm of the familiar and what we want
to do is in understanding it is actually
move towards the unfamiliar right and
and the watched leg at least completes
with my American friends right you start
saying that stuff and literally they'll
get they'll just get pissed and like
accusation 'el and what do you tell me
but i did but the thing is the thing I'm
speaking like an American but then again
you know the word thing is not clear
what the thing is yeah um and actually
the thing has benign as it seems to come
along at all right that's the thing it's
quite horrifying them some to things to
thing to points to issues
Heidegger wishes to think negativity as
Hegel does even more radically more
dangerously and said yes negativity you
know he doesn't use this word because
it's directed at beings but still he
says if negativity then ask catastrophe
catastrophe English which means there's
actually something that's turning around
here when genuine profound negativity
it's then something really is turning
around and turned as a turning way of
turning and overturning and he thinks
that this is not really the case with
Hegel's negativity and this and so he
wants to understand is to understand the
negative is closer to the creek tote
Dane on that which is horrifying that
which is horrible
ah that which is completely no which is
the in the tragic sense the moment when
all is lost but still the tragedy
continuous rightness the early purse
continues when it's already all horrible
our Antigone is just the entire story is
pain after pain after pain the pain
doesn't go away and it doesn't dissolve
either just there's no results at the
end of it and that's the Dane on the
moment of day known is when it's clear
that this will end and that's a pain for
everyone involved
yeah but there's no resolve there's no
way around it it's now just going to
continue
yeah and that's how he wants to think
the negative but then you said you know
it's difficult for Americans I would
have to point out that very likely it's
the same over here in Europe and perhaps
even especially in Germany there is
almost no scholarship on Heidegger that
would take all these questions seriously
the question of being yeah well and
nowhere nowhere but almost nowhere I
mean there are a few people in there um
but where is you know there is a
question of being well I'm so I've
written a book with the subtitle an
answer to the question of being that's
the question
our and he says very often for the task
is to try and articulate a response to
war yeah and this is not I there's no
absolute response to it it's a finite
attempt at it and there will be better
ones but that must be the attempt when
we take it seriously everything else is
just you know something that's
interesting or yes there's a whole
program of turning Zion squishy to the
hiding of being not the history of being
the tidings of being also in Germany
just into something that's in the past
and trust these various ways of
interpreting being yeah well wouldn't
you say that's that's just perspectivism
but this was the main problem of gaddama
a gaddama was incapable of actually
pointing out some anything else in a
Nietzsche
perspectivism in his his the first
version of this truth and method right
um but to say that you know it's all
just perspectival it's basically it's
just saying that everything's more or
less contingent yeah and when everything
is well as contingent well you know one
has to be careful about what sophistry
is why people think and sophistry has
got to do with rhetoric yes but actually
this office do something else
yeah the Sophists are those who think
against thinking who put on the pedestal
who fetishize or tried or argue in terms
of contingency that can come in many
different forms so the mere contingency
is found when there is no necessity to
so I want to say it again the first
paragraph is the necessity of repeating
this question oh that's the first
paragraph of the time then of course we
can we can talk about whether this is
the proper approach post hanging etc but
then why is this necessity given because
post can't have - can't what does the
revolution of con can't is not in the
business of writing a benign
epistemology con would not be conned if
he just said oh this is how you
recognize an object why Hugh was not in
that business either Hume pointed out
that if we give up on reason and
categories will we end up with is the
complete absurd position of the self
being a heap of impressions and I don't
know whether it'll Sun will rise
tomorrow huh or if reason goes unbound
as with John Locke than it ends up in
mere fancy which means you know then you
have matter that's also spiritual I
don't actually need the external world
etc which is what Berkeley said about
John Locke but what is what Khan
realizes here maybe without realizing it
is that one all of these thinkers do
especially in all the way back to two
Parmenides of course but but even more
so in in
in what we now call the modern early
modern period is to simply presuppose
dogmatically the identity between being
and thought the critical philosophy was
on a system right critique asks for the
Basques how is this presupposition
possible which is the identity between
being and thought right which was just
assumed before yeah yeah never even
question so the critical that's where it
sets in but then all all hell breaks
loose with this yeah that's the
revolution of thought and now what post
and all philosophy has to do if it
doesn't want to be dogmatic right it has
to become it has to be able to think of
its presuppositions yeah and we hang
them in this is what hiding it does or
tries to do right and this is what
Heidegger tries to do with the entire
philosophy up until to him right then we
get problems of concealment the
attachments yeah but that's that's for
another I'm there's that I think there's
I think what I just really kind of
gotten what you're saying is is that
what philosophy does is it reveals what
presupposes what you took is
self-evident or weren't even noticing
that anything was presupposed what makes
that evident right and obviouly strike
in my experience years ago it questions
something that I wasn't even
I wasn't even um I wasn't even not
oriented towards but but when at the
moment it's questioned every bill that I
was standing on something that was
giving everything and that's that like
shaking up that uncanny nough seems to
be a lot of
the way I think that probably Heidegger
is getting at with with anxiety and
being in time of it reveals the the
uncanny Ness of the ground
oh that you're you're standing on things
think that make allow things to reveal
themselves that are at work that you
could not know about and you could not
know that you didn't know about but you
were given by something about finding
like kind of coming coming awakened that
seems to be very similar to the the
awakening of philosophy itself on some
level right look what's important those
in terms of highly cuz we have to
understand who it is that he's
responding to yeah right speaking of the
human gene called them Berkeley IDEs
yeah um for them Heidegger apparently
just talks about me walking around
feeling anxious because I'm in the state
of total world collapse called death
yeah okay yeah but you know that's
that's four that's kitchen psychology as
we could say in Kentucky
that's that psychology for the masses
yeah and and Heidegger called psychology
by the way psycho technics which is
interesting reference but I think a
response to the entirety of philosophy
and Heidegger points out for example in
this in the essay the principle of
identity there's that state and actually
the spring of identity he says that the
the thought of
entity that a can equal a what even what
kind of presupposition thought must make
here without going into it too much yeah
for thinking to find out that it has
always already made the presupposition
off the identity between being in
thought it took thinking two thousand
years he says this to get to this point
with cod and then fifty yeah cool be
shelling and Hegel or Trent try to bring
it together again especially Hegel yeah
and and actually this is why Eagle
philosophizes without presuppositions
without any horizon the signs of logic
eagles masterpiece is a logic that moves
forward by the categories collapsing
necessarily because the understanding
wants to hold onto them but reason sees
that you cannot hold on to them yeah so
you know you start with being pure being
yeah and then the understanding wants to
say something being pure being but then
it already shows some activity you know
it's that connection where the where the
the actuality is supreme right with with
Hegel versus the possibility yeah yeah
but we have to be yes um yeah but we'll
have to be I think I have to think about
that yes but also but what what angle
does is he just like Heidegger takes
into consideration yeah the entirety of
philosophy because communities stays
here at being as being as being more or
less yeah but where it's nothing with
nothing but it can't be nothing with
nothing because nothing will come up
right it's just like death who
existential terms death will come to
haunt you if you don't if you don't
consider death an epoch that wants to
know nothing about nothingness
we'll be haunted by what by nihilism um
what Hegel shows though is a deal that
no category actually remains just a
state it's all activity
all right negativity is activity spirit
is negativity ontology in traditional
sense
that's what's mystic Ida to think of the
the mind as a racecar racecar chitons a
thinking thing it's not a thing
yes it's it's in a continuous uber game
passing over and passing back and this
is what what Heidegger responds to is
the critical philosophy of Kant and the
response to it by a goal and Schelling
especially and high niggas trying to
show that what all of this is grounded
in grounded in careful but what all of
this is grounded is design and is also
and then we can get into consumer and
etc - but no but it's it's when we take
Heidegger seriously um that we begin to
to see that it isn't arbitrary ready you
you cannot one cannot just take up a
text and philosophy and read into it
whatever contingently comes to mind yeah
um that's that that's a really a
destruction of off the tradition and
that basically you know when we speak of
the meaning crisis that that's what has
to do with it right as it becomes
arbitrary yeah we cannot just take up a
text from Parmenides and then say oh but
we can reinterpret this in this many
ways and Heinicke doesn't do it as aina
haina casis what all of this so he
doesn't say this is what happened here
and I'm just gonna go over here and do
this entirely new thing ya know he says
there's always been something at the
heart of it which has been forgotten but
that's not a pejorative yeah it's
forgotten necessarily yeah because
because of the
of the movement of the thought itself
and then it becomes transparent to
itself just like with card in this
critical instance Asif he noticed that
it had always made the presupposition of
the identity between being in thought
after what you have to you have to look
at even more presuppositions and hiding
it says that this is the shared memory
in which thinking participates which
thinking is the gathering of thinking it
means to think that which has been
thought this is exactly is a different
formulation for this right but this is
what it has to do and this is why I
think there is this ah this the
relationship between or as Heidegger
says in the freiburg freiburg talks the
finit elective affinity between death
and thinking insofar as thinking is
always under threat of dying off um and
is always on the threat of falling into
another concealment but it's also under
threat of trying to bring everything to
a sheer light that forgets shadow and
darkness right in this sense because I'm
seeing behind you there um the School of
Athens by a referendum I mean look I
have as you know I have this photograph
of this painting on my channel and it's
quite appealing it's aesthetically
pleasing etc but what is the Renaissance
the greenish I meant oh the in exhaust
it's got nothing to do with you know oh
this is a wonderful time where
everything was so bright in meaning the
Renaissance is the time where people
like Leonardo da Vinci and Donna Braun
or begin to think
Tejano Brunel writes a one of his essays
is on the shadows of ideas what comes
back in the Renaissance is exactly this
interplay between yes lights and
darkness and shadows yeah um and this is
also why my lecture series is called the
coming of any source I need to be able
to think post enlightenment yeah I'm
what it means to think in chatters oh by
the way why is why is can't I know of
clever and enlightener someone who
clears up the sky not not only you know
not morality it's such a robot he is an
enlightening a clearer because he clears
thinking discloses to thought itself it
has always made this presupposition now
for the high daguerreian reader this
means there was something quote-unquote
concealed yeah you always could consume
it and then hiding a ceaseless and
radicalizes just thought of concealment
and that then is called the
concentration yeah off of it is death
yeah yeah right right
and by thinking it we don't want to make
it available yeah where you don't mint
it's not about making it operational
right if only I just and then then how
then I can deal with death or then we
can overcome it I don't know it's you
you let it occur yeah and this letting
lets you in - yeah this other mode of
being that no longer wants to control
but lets occur doesn't the Lassen higher
are the letting be yeah yeah really it's
just it's ultimately a form of piety
which means a love for ancestry
there's also form of humility all right
all right
modesty yeah modesty in thought yeah but
this is this but this is not arbitrary
right because this is the task of
mortals who who have unwanted powers
right and this is precisely what get
style doesn't doesn't have access to
right because get Kasatka style is all
about it can't it can't reveal
concealment it it's that quality and
basically what I'm hearing you saying
and what I get from reading philosophy
and Heidegger and is that there's a that
there's basically
the good stuff okay is all in is is in
the hidden and in that in that are what
gives us meaning is not know revealed
like what's shining it's obvious in the
light which but that which is concealed
in being oriented and awake to that
concealment right that withdrawal but in
in such a way that like you know this is
I think what if I were to kind of say it
in my own words like with the glass
glass and I like the sense of it's like
allowing it's a it's allowing you could
say the unknown to become present
without making it known without turning
it into the known like that sense of the
the negative space or the the to be
attuned into that like RH seems to be
precisely the very thing that doesn't
even notice that it's not attuned into
that right yeah and it's very important
so geese daily is the concentration of
positing it has nothing to do with
machines yeah machines are a result of
this yeah yes off the technical yeah so
you know the goose Dell is not TV I mean
it's a we have to be careful because to
some degree we hold the will to power in
our hands with these things but we don't
want to represent or imagine gift L as
the machine world or the world of
algorithms etc what the work with not
really a world records it's nothing
human about it um what were the
algorithms do though is they posit they
posit the world by means of the
parameters of time and space now here's
what's eerie about the old cond
um
he notices that metaphysics has always
made this presupposition presupposition
pre positing literally right yeah this
hi pool this prima thesis this is
meaning to posit which is fine because
we need to posit it something yes you
have need to posit just to build a house
but yeah in the thought is rather
difficult to act to articulate reality
or to tackle a being which is not the
same we have to be careful but let's
just say for now like this so can't
notices this and that's the earthquake
that is can't which we are suffering but
then how does he respond to it he wants
to hold on to because ultimately you
always have to find something to hold on
to
he wants to hold on to the logic of
positing the knowledge shake off
instrumental rationality as we now call
it of a knowledge of power it's in the
knowledge it's in the fits how from a
Hegelian stance it's in how we
articulate ourselves and in life in
nature on the logical plane then we
begin to act and be in the world and
what con does is he sees this
presupposition but then when you read
the first critique its posits it's one
positing after another and it's now it's
at some point set up in such a way that
what we no longer have access to with
God is what things in themselves yeah
yeah this is for how to erase these
essays building drilling thinking and
the thing coming back to the thing in
itself in itself with an essence of
itself with an Uzi ax of itself because
here's the weird thing
the Natural Sciences and their laws one
thing if you like they never look at is
nature
Nature herself is not visible in Natural
Sciences because of the natural
scientists look at our abstract laws
yeah they look at for example very
simple very almost to Bernard you put it
there's a cat and as a stone they weigh
the same you dropped them both it
doesn't matter what's being dropped in
what Falls what matters is the mass and
the volume and the weight we know what
they look at is an abstract law which is
not visible it's metaphysical in the
proper sense of the word right nature
has always already turned away from what
the operations of gifts tell which just
posits something yeah yeah about it yeah
which which we call models model by
which we then access the world yeah or
the world view yeah the world picture
yeah which is not really a picture at
all it's a mathematical model is that is
that kind of like it does that link into
the one of the reasons why the more
technological devices for example the
more disappears the more you can't like
when the phones really being the phone
you don't notice the phone you're it and
the moment doesn't work it's not like a
you know like a windmill right a
windmill it stops working but you leave
it there it still gathers world it still
has meeting and it's old in it right
where is like something that shines
through yeah yes and it's just and it's
just this mill yeah yes okay I will now
step down from the the higher you know
the abstract what I just talked about is
the three years ago I traveled through
the this fine island here and we went
down I went down with my parents to sand
ice and tin tetra which is at the very
far western end of this island
I think it's Cornwall so
one of these faces beautiful down there
so ten th one is might have been the
castle of King Arthur
Tim tension is a touristy place at the
castle a burger doesn't really stand
anymore but then we hike across and
along the the coastline there's a
there's very very English cause it's not
the not the chalk white covers but it's
quite quite rocky and some kind of dark
stone I wouldn't know which one so he
kept walking there was there was no one
there we hiked down towards a small aa
river that here
I was flowing into the ocean and as he
walked down we decided to we also had no
V no phone service nothing work which is
you know rarely the case anymore and
then we hiked up the tiny River and came
across an old mill wall timber which had
been abandoned hundreds of years ago who
knows it was no it was it was ruin
just the ruin but the sensation very
much water there is still something
guarded here you could something was
still lingering an old world still shone
through it was shining still this thing
I cannot tell apart from any other yeah
yeah yes and it is it is it will be
forgotten yes a minute I buy a new one
yes because I can download and upload
and to the cloud and blah blah blah
whatever there is on it in terms of
piece of data and this is how we now
treat all of so-called history history
is just a file age system right a filing
system sorry a pigeon-holed filing
system menu and the same with you know
we can say a bit provocatively there is
no history of philosophy there is only
thinking yeah and either you are open to
access the Avenue towards thinking or
you are stuck on the level where it's
just arbitrary historical observations
about is it this kind of ism or that
kind of ISM there is a necessity in
Heidegger cestus again in the gain there
is a necessity to his thinking and that
it takes thinking thousands of years at
the same time he also says something
which is remarkable an important for us
thinking only just now begins because
it's twisting free to some degree also
from its own presuppositions in a sense
that it doesn't liberate itself and then
just grow must really know but it's
becoming more and more transparent to it
what had remained concealed and if there
is always consumed and also at work or
withdrawal yeah so that is that's that's
what kinda cult Amelie calls another
beginning and all this talk about
collapse and the you know hanukkah's
very critical of Spengler for example
the decline of the West because for him
that's just a representational account
Oh history comes in cycles you know it
goes up and it goes down it's almost
it's almost silly to say this there's
lot of talk right now about
collapse there's a lot of talk right now
about at the apocalypse I make the
distinction by the way between
apocalyptic thinking an apocalyptic
representation representation and
imagination you know it actually gravels
it drives on these visions of fire
burning and entire cities collapsing and
kind of this is almost like you know you
can see the Sun on the political
spectrum on all sides people want it
seems an apocalyptic thinking this is a
completely different mode it's it it it
doesn't actively look for but it is open
for openings in will be usually called
history which is not just in you know a
succession of events but is there's
always a tiding there is always
something that announces itself which we
respond always already and it I think
that brings about a certain modesty also
because the other you know the
apocalyptic collapse fantasies yeah
they either want everything to collapse
for everything to burn or they want
everything to collapse for to have the
the the perfect utopia coming later on
and not none all of this to me at least
forgets death and forgets the other
right this this this other way of being
and and also what ultimately it means to
be human and we can you know I think he
did its then probably more to be human
means to to build yes and to to Elias
but then also to let go yeah and to
recognize how deeply you already are let
go right that's the that's the thing
about like I noticed for that seems to
be at least a
for me when I feel the most the sense or
the intimacy of being as has to do often
and this is this is what happens in in
philosophy and poetry where you realize
the thing that you were sensing into
that was like just beyond your capacity
to see was that which was just most near
right and that kind of recognition that
oh I'm already always the all kind of
that sense of already always finding
myself already begun underway right this
kind of quality of how even what no
matter what I was representing there was
an intelligibility right that kind of
didn't need me right to be going on
right in that when that's revealed
there's something really there's huh
it's it's humbling but it's also
it's yeah it kind of gets it gets it
that sense of like both in intimacy like
a really deep intimacy but also
transparent to kind of an inexhaustible
'ti that's really near yeah because
that's everything that you're talking
about is like on some on some level is
is is articulating or pointing to what
is the case right but is concealed like
on some level is concealed from me
right the and you can look back on it I
know people a lot of times you know they
get this kind of awakening like when
they read about history right of like
where they recognize their way of
thinking about something wasn't just
isn't self-evident like the case that
there's a history to it
but that worse there's something that
were we're always responding to and it
does seem like you know it's thinking
about this to about you know how the way
that Heidegger talks about listening and
my understanding right you know where he
says perhaps it's a good idea there we
go we can begin to hear things that we
don't already think right and and I was
thinking of
that just in in talking to people or and
what I do in circling where there's this
this deeply moving thing that happens
for people that they they talk about
this this experience of being deeply
seeing and that's that phrase is that
phrases a little bit paradoxical because
it seems to conjure up a sense of like
kind of something to then see but I
actually think it's the opposite of that
people don't don't have the experience
of being deeply seen by when you repeat
back to them right the thing that's
available to be seen it's more like when
you can start to hear with them the
thing that they're that that they're
that they've been at the deepest level
caring for and caring about like the the
sense of what's beyond the horizon when
you can go somehow that you gets
revealed yeah that people the beyond the
thing that they can't put into words
that gets revealed is people have this
oh my god I feel deeply seen right which
which sounds which I think it's elicit a
function of like what like harkening
listening really seems to be oriented
around right which would be very
different than from the other psycho
techniques right yeah yeah like
psychoanalysis so-called yeah which is a
weird term by the way because analysis
means to take apart right yeah it's just
pointing them out yeah that you know
just said it so let's see what that does
with it right right right which
presupposes there's already that which
to take apart and then yeah but just to
take apart yeah yeah yeah yeah which is
the opposite of being seem through
listening yeah
yes and then then we would have to dwell
on we could
um on the importance of hearing in
Heraclitus right ok Mualla Telugu Haku
Santa's homologated soft honest in hemp
antenna
not to me but to the Lagos having heard
well it is wise to say soft honest in
Ramallah gain hemp Antonina that one is
many let me out of one many the all
unifying one this is by the way would
HIGHLY get things also all unifying one
we always already hear the logos yeah we
always already hear it but don't perhaps
always hearken to it and respond to it
right and what the as you know highly it
was in touch with the Salah con people
made out boss that psychiatrists there
and they were outraged in the beginning
because he said you can't begin with the
subject object economy and but the what
would so be being seen but seen is just
some some isolated subject or perhaps
seen as someone who is in this all
unifying one yeah which out of which
many and to which we here so that it
becomes wise why is not in this
intellectual sense of knowing a lot but
it becomes why so fond Sophia deeper
profound wisdom that's addresses yeah
all the time
um that's perhaps this being seen yeah
that's being articulated and being said
by right what many right I'm bike and
that's that that's this other form of of
meditation - yeah which now today means
to sit in the room on your own
it means to take into care everything
that isn't so far that is which is not a
concrete entity in this kind of
representational sites right yeah but
exactly again in this
in this harmony or this concert of in
this Symphony of existence which again
according to her cleitus only arises
from out of the net which died after a
rain that which bursts apart and then
comes together yeah and and yeah I it's
it's it's fascinating to witness this a
bit right for me um because it's it's
it's where all of the cycle things just
the cycle they're not there well they're
not there because what they're looking
is eyes are looking at a case yeah yeah
um a case in the sense of no you you are
classified as this and you take if your
psychiatrist if you take this pill and
I'm sure that you know pills at some
point of perhaps necessary yeah um but
it doesn't it never it does it get to
it's a heart of the problem what is
depression right what is depression
what is melancholia why does dura paint
melancholia what is it for us today
oh you're not functioning um what why
schizophrenia prevalent in what we call
capitalism or what its capital it does
exactly actually not asked it doesn't
come up oh and I think it cannot come up
because ultimately it's about
containment it's about taming yeah yeah
yeah the the thought of fight again in
death is another one yeah it's not to
tame it is to let loose and let's see
then what happens because weirdly enough
it is more then Oh with an allowance for
well here II as well that it doesn't
and us that much right yeah the way to
do it one has to find for himself yeah
yeah the the high to get as you know the
later hiding is all about dwelling and
Huntley I give rather thinking then
becomes a craft something of the hands
to UM how do we build not housing but
dwelling grounds for mortals yeah so we
don't deny death it's that it's almost
too simple to say it right if not we're
just units of consumption units of
capital that to which capital flows the
only neighborhoods to look like
neighborhoods that's the strangest thing
yes every youth like housing division or
something going on I'm like yeah they're
literally building all of those houses
in a neighborhood to look like a
neighborhood and you can feel them not
being a neighborhood they are there to
represent or look like being a
neighborhood it's the strangest yeah
it's like that the hollowness like of it
is just almost nauseating for me deep
yeah but did but you know it it needs a
church at the center of it yes and the
church has a graveyard yes and the
church is the place and you know
speaking of Western European it'll be a
mosque or a synagogue for example
somewhere else or a temple all right it
could be a Buddhist temple as well but
let's say the church it's it's where the
child is baptized where the couple is
where you get married or where you're
buried well I'm one up by the way just
you know speaking from personally one of
the beautiful things about this country
here is that they don't or not very
often at least get rid of their old
cemeteries you walk around even a place
like London Eye
yes I remember that about London yeah
yeah yeah
recently I went to William Blake's grave
which is an old graveyard in the middle
actually off the financial district and
I left a flower or a stone actually
another flower stone on his on his
tombstone which is a very very yeah you
there these cemeteries that that that
they turn into parks but then every
grave is just left to its own devices
and collapses slowly into itself there's
how you cos of the earth regaining and
kind of the honors of you know the war
lies kept in such and such searching of
this and the Lamia he lies professor
here there most of these honors mean I
mean almost nothing very very quickly to
us perhaps some of the you see as well
but um it is in this in this yeah I I
wonder you know we can have to spend on
this at some point and in what sense
this being seen is outside the specter
or the matrix of representation yeah
exactly right exactly where it perhaps
it also has to do with some to some
degree I'm not sure we can talk with
mortality to but it is I think outside
of representation it's no longer you're
not looked at a case like this yeah well
you know you you you you show these
kinds of well I think your daddy was
mean to you um or you you did you want
to be your mother
you know these weird schemas that we
know haven't developed
oh this is must be you know we walk
around through representational schemas
right well that must be unconscious well
that must be something you experience in
your oh you know no maybe there's always
something else at work of which you know
which there are there are terrible cases
you know really terrible in human beings
are as I con rightly says radically evil
evil at the root da you
things that happen right in the world -
very often unfortunately because people
thought they were doing good and they
wanted to do good yeah but but then
again I I wonder sometimes that perhaps
you know people talk about the the rise
of people who are depressed yeah well
what is it yeah that is depression yeah
pointing to what is what it was what is
what is that what is it no how does
depression know to respond as depression
that's that that's the part like I've
noticed with and I think it's the thing
that you're talking about is is like the
listening to someone really happens when
it's like one is like if they're paying
attention to anything there's a response
right yeah that that's like it's if it's
it it's precisely that it's like what do
you respond to - that you would be
talking about this what is it that how
does how does attention know to attend
to this what is this
and what's that which is worthy of that
response like a mystery you know what's
interesting is like you start to to
things it's like the one is it starts to
reveal
a caer an implicit care on on their
behalf that their respondent that
they're responding is so it reveals on
one level this kind of the horizons the
backgrounds of what's going on with them
which is usually historical on some
level right
just there comporting in that way ravit
also reveals a world in which they're
attempting to reveal but there's also
the sense of like that it reveals that
revealing is happening so there's this
quality of just they actually start yeah
actually I think what it is it may
actually be where they actually hear
themselves as as something that is
beyond their representation right and
it's that kind of sense of like oh my
god like more than I can I am more than
I can conceive well you know what one
could say miss Logan I'm gonna have to
be careful with it's the being kicks in
and representation drops this is to
simply put but it does sound like a
great t-shirt yeah
you can have it love it too long for a
coffee cup ya know but it's it's it's
right one of the things I've said as
well and it's I'm not sure with it I've
been able to because I don't think I've
made it clear enough um is it what
perhaps we are witnessing and happen
it's only just now you know showing
itself really really more too horribly
them before is the apocalypse of the
subject its opening up to is its its
utmost maximum of what it can control
and wants to control and manage and
finds itself I think increasingly
incapacitated to do so but this constant
talk of crisis as a crisis in everything
however the word has become basically
meaningless
well it seems to be could be that deep
the worlds of power has pushed to an
utmost limit where it finds it it's no
longer powerful it can no longer will
control it would have to say
death let's just put it like this
without facing death everything is
turning to a crisis without ever
becoming a crisis and a crisis is a
moment of decision and what you're
describing I can only as a as a as an
and someone who listens and spectator so
now a participant in it and I couldn't
be asked those but what I think is
perhaps showing there is that what we
call subjectivity in the philosophical
sense which means an enclosed Ness the
split from the world and to some degree
now of course in a schizophrenic sense
of a split from oneself because you know
the way people talk is of themselves in
the representational manner as if there
is something behind them which which is
from which point they speak about
themselves in this reflect constant
reflective manner um then that drops
away oh and then this sense of being
seen shines through which which which
reveals another way of being human if
you like right a deeper way which is
what I think it would call design way
it's shown that it's always already
being with others right it's always
already been being in the world yeah
yeah I hope in it there is that quality
to of you know it's like I think your
own young talks about this it where yeah
a lot of people read young and then they
they they kind of like they don't
realize how much he's talking about
especially with the shadow right the
notion of the shadow which is the first
thing that you contend with it when you
do Union analysis and stuff like that
and people usually think of like you get
to the shadow by reflecting on yourself
right and you was like no people forget
that he's writing this in the context of
of what he's discovering in a
relationship with somebody that it's
it's in and I never it just recently I
started to realize like oh yeah this
ties into how genuine listening and see
genuinely being with somebody begins is
precisely when you realize that you're
it's that you're projecting on to the
other person great and then you start to
see that in a certain sense oh that I'm
projecting I wasn't actually listening
to you right it's that hearing that you
weren't hearing as the moment that
hearing begins right it's uh that's the
thing about listening this is this is
one of the trickiest things of of
teaching people how to listen
that's all you can't you all you can do
is to show people that they're not in
the moment they can hear that they're
not hearing yes is the moment that that
that that that something else breaks
through and no yes but it is similarly
thinking when our borrow our mo artists
they say is is a different one it's the
one of positivism we're just hearing by
you know by using our own tech substrate
here as here as receivers of sound waves
yeah you know I'm hearing you cuz you
and I we're having a conversation of
course I'm hearing you well I I'm
listening um we're of course I'm
thinking I mean you know I've been
thinking about it
you know Chinese food tonight I don't
know uh or of course I'm thinking
because I have the all these ideas about
what to do I mean you know just just the
fact that you can say idea or in this
image manner as we do now or is it
there's this website call that people
will know at Pinterest but you can
collect ideas about what your perfect
home would look like you know no offense
to anyone who uses it but the fact that
you can say the word idea this old quick
work and Plato is right behind you there
on the painting this old world word and
this old world too shines through
screams through almost through this word
in this world of ideas that's run by
ideas what is going on we are this being
trapped in the cave is something that
keeps me up at night
but did there's always this that the
this moment when it's about philosophy
then why is it important because it's
it's all there it's all been thought you
have to think it again for our epoch
there is no coincidence that we're
running that a planetary system is being
run that's trying on ideas etc we it's
it's an apparent availability apparent
availability and positiveness positivity
when it comes in many forms of wisdom I
mean the something's being posited as
available and present but then of course
you know you could just as a joke people
who say think positively there's no
thinking thinking positively thinking
what would it think it's just positing
is literally just positing so I think
it's just saying something yeah thinking
begins in negation Spinoza says
ominously seminars us thing out see
every determination is a negation then
there is no determination without
negation where why would you determine
anything without negating it to be not
something else
and in the highest form of this for
Hegel in the dialectics is which cannot
be formalized right the nothing cannot
be formalized is the negation of the
negation that's the activity of
negativity and that spirit spirit is
negativity yeah yeah that roams freely
in history and it's upon us to grasp
this conceptually and then to quarrel
over and fight over what the meaning of
freedom is freedom is not the given
you're not given freedom by some
Constitution or or here's your negative
freedom now you can do whatever you want
oh it's yeah freedom is something that's
fought over precisely for this reason
right is that it's not a given yeah it's
like it's almost it's it's you know
reading with Chris
reading reading this Socratic dialogues
like that it's it's it seems like what
Socrates is doing is easy yes sorry but
look this is philosophically very
important they're people people people
people with people so I will not say
people because it's a bit awful this is
so apologies in general I think the
assumption is that there are two worlds
in Plato there aren't and Plato's does
not say that the tree this tree over
here
is not is is not really he says it's men
on men on it's not fully being but in
this not fully being it is yeah it is
because it's not fully but it then
becomes full insofar as the thinking
being participates in this occurrence
and must articulate the being of this
being yes right right yeah this is what
all of thinking has to do we are
participants and suffering participants
of this ongoing occurrence and to state
with Heinicke being is rare not
everything that's out there
Polly is yeah right and this is also why
I'm in this time that's accelerating and
exploding everybody wants to be and then
it turns out as representational it's
like this and it's like that and
schematized and I can be easily rehashed
etc you can make all these points about
capital than to you can it and it's
becoming a bit of a platonic Kay friend
we're sitting in these rooms and we're
looking at each other's screens and
avatars unless that's the danger of it
um but at the same time is we when when
you read these dialogue would you I mean
I don't know I didn't know what you want
to say but it's very important to point
out that height that Plato does not
speak of two different worlds right but
that we always have to think negation
yeah in order to actually arrive at all
that will be now called reality yeah
reality is not just here here's all
these things yes yes this reality
reality arises from out of negation yeah
out of also ups Tolson right um for
Eagle it would be up chosen which is
pushing away yeah pushing away from the
immediate which is exactly the story of
the cave by just looking at the shadows
these people are not ever dealing with
being they're not ever the the the the
the the prisoners of the cave as it were
then I never you even becoming free
right right but they think they are free
because they can remember us you know
the the right order of the shadows pass
right by right but it's actually in
pushing away from it in yeah saying no
yeah and withdrawal yeah that the
original concealment begins to
unconcealed or a while then with
Heidegger again just coming back into
the cave appreciating the concealment
yes yes and that's kind of what another
thing I've noticed against in these in
these dialogues as Socrates he's like
you know basically asking a question and
then they start talking about it and
like everything at like
all of this information gets it gets
more frustrating and they go around then
Socrates doesn't even know what the
virtue is and and at some point there's
this a pot like this aporia where the
thing that that can't be said in the
dialogue becomes present right this kind
of sense of where we're and I think it's
that sense of
of all those kind of apparatus questions
that been bringing you up to the limit
of your represent eight you're
representing right yes yes to the
represent so I would not stop at the
aporia right that's often the mistake
that's middle is just all ends in the
poor you know really does gaming of it
yes exactly exactly in there it gets it
gets symbolized right I think it gets
symbolized in and usually at the end of
the talks like these dialogues yeah none
of the questions were answered yet that
people want to send their kids to spend
time with more time with Socrates right
people see better there's that that
quality of the neck the the negativity
if you know right so hello that one you
realize that we didn't realize that we
were circling around but what the so
called a poori argument but you see how
how the reception always works old it's
just a poetic and it's just all
paradoxical everything is absurd blah
blah blah know what's showing itself to
be absurd is what was portraying itself
as perfectly rational which is very good
the logic of the understanding which
proclaimed that it can corroborate
exactly what so-called word should by
itself is but then you have to begin to
think no longer in terms of what someone
does or someone says or someone or Pines
but no you have to begin to think in
terms of principles and that's why they
end in so-called aporia's because they
don't step up to the level of reason of
logos itself but staying on the level of
trying to represent and making available
yeah and easily of course a model right
it's something that can be and this is
what this is why so it's so absurd to
say we should have we should have built
high daguerreian AI I mean the the what
is this even supposed to mean a high
daguerreian AI an AI that's actually
being in the world I mean the one think
of the 20th century who wanted nothing
else but to be completely outside the
clutches of instrumentalities
and you cannot make his thinking
operational there's no model there's no
formula that can be taken from Heidegger
and and and even Hegel is even more you
one can unfortunately an easily attack
Hegel on these grounds it's as you know
some people did very very prominently
Karl Marx thought that he could use
Hickam dialectics to see the future but
that's that's a perfect example of what
representation is it assumes it can see
the future just by the right method for
example but the utopian wonderful state
which is inevitably come ah it if all we
do is get the dialectics right that's
for presentation yeah and I to get you
you cannot make him instrumental you you
it's completely impossible
yeah it it's and in this sense its
operatic but it's only a poetic for a
representation not for thinking thinking
itself is always on the way Heidegger
says yeah but it is is it's coming it's
about coming home um and it's it's
ultimately about dwelling and dwelling
means to come home it means to come home
but going out and then coming home going
out going out as this negation right
this moment of saying no leaving the
cave yeah coming back in right and this
is I think these are the moments of of
moments but this is what what finding is
concealed and guarded and concentrated
and sheltered in death yeah yeah what's
is something about is something I just
wanted to talk with you about to you
know in your I'm reading I'm reading
your teachers book the weirdness of
being de Gennaro oh and that's a that is
it that is not an easy book at all but
it's it's uh it's not an easy book at
all in a I'm appreciating it I'm like
I'm appreciating it a lot well one of
things that he said in in your last
videos and it struck me was that
Heidegger towards the end of his life
was like writing in these journals ten
hours at he was thinking ten hours a day
in the 32 yeah
it's done at the end of his life it was
peak actually right like it he was just
in his you know honest the hut I had the
hi to Gary and Hut right like out there
that the journals that are now being
published that you get every month or
something like there's a there because
half of his work hasn't been published
right and and it's in these little
notebooks that you can actually get as
they translate it correct you were
telling me that yeah yeah yeah I guess
well not a state transit but some of the
notebooks of being published in the
heidegger's asides he ends on once a
year some some shorter notes to you
right
not every month though I saw some I saw
some pictures of of it you know like
there a lot of them are some of them are
drawings and they have arrows and
there's it what
you
what is he in a certain sense what is he
doing when he's doing that like 10 hours
a day right thinking and I guess people
he would like people would come and they
would think for 10 hours a day right
what is what's your sense of what is he
doing when he's doing that in those
journals like to the extent that you've
read um yeah I mean so I mean some of
the some of them are some one of them is
contributions to philosophy by three
it's a few fee written in 38 published I
think in the 80s another one is does
that Agnes
published I think ten years ago
written in the 40s and this is where
Heidegger begins to think in terms of
Agnes which I will leave on trans I
think event is a poor translation but I
use is well I shouldn't really say what
is but he comes he comes into this
thinking enhanced
begins to see something where he thinks
something the withdrawal concealment
that needs to be thought so it just it
needs to be thought it thinks in me says
at some point to his brother that
there's nothing he can do about this and
this is what's so strange to to modern I
think human beings because you know you
have this opinion I have this opinion I
think it's this isn't you think it's
that ISM but it maybe it isn't maybe it
is really that some things have to be
thought and there has to be some
thoughts have to be thorn and they have
to be thought thoroughly and this is
what he does knowing however that
nothing that is thought and place we had
exist near this as well can ever be
fully recorded we should not conflate
the books someone writes with the
thought yeah we still have to think when
we read the books the books are gateways
they're necessary
we need books we need we need records
too but that's not all there is right
right is an echo of another realm
perhaps - or other realms that we have
to take on and so there's a necessity to
this writing it's a necessity right
there if there is a necessity to it then
you will simply have to write it was
necessary because not because Heidegger
thought it necessary but because thought
itself thought itself also a sailor
sense again thought itself thought
itself necessarily in this way yeah yeah
Heidi get those of the thinker as you
know who keeps coming back to Anam knows
oniy the goddess of memory to the muses
and he mentions them not arbitrarily
again homer addresses the muses hundra
my and the P Musa pollute Rapanos Philip
LaPlante a patriot commentary that's the
first two lines of the Odyssey sing to
me muse or off the man manifold so it's
yeah this this it's list it's it's
listening to something not something
with you but listening and then having
to because thought itself now hairston
reset this before Kant stumbles upon
this presupposition all of thought had
made and it Heidegger says they can I
said this before it took thinking 2,000
years to begin to see this
presupposition yeah it takes it doesn't
say it takes thinkers he doesn't say it
took it took some pesky chairman up up
in Prussia and conics back to oh by the
way I think no no it took thinking 2,000
years yeah it's it's thinking it's other
things itself yeah but we have to
respond and correspond to it as long as
you a human being wide because according
to Aristotle reals or lock on Iran which
is not the rational animal but the
living being that finds a stance in
logos on
which is related by the way to the word
scholar which is only poorly translated
as letter so let's get this brother
it's Cola it's fighting scholar ah yes
so finitude is calling me
which means I'm hungry yes great great
talking with you as as usual as always
as always really really good I mean what
we should discuss further next time
uh-huh
maybe also for the record if you like is
on the on representation
yeah and seeing and being seen yes and
then I'll well maybe we'll flip it a bit
you know
I'll listen more and talk less this this
may be actually the thing this may be
actually the thing that would be good
for me to to my piece on the writing
actually yeah cuz this is what it is
central and in what circling seems to be
yeah that's two of them
alright great thanks thanks for the
madness
they're good like tuning it and hearing
the bad baby for the dislodgement yeah
that's just me in a regular Tuesday
night yes